<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A] caveat for wives to love their husbands or, Pleasant news from hell. Written in Italian by that grand politician Nicholas Machiavel and now translated into English for a Christmas-gigg.</title>
            <author>Machiavelli, Niccolò, 1469-1527.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B43389</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">297426152</idno>
  <idno type="VID">208141</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240897784</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 297426152</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 297426152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M132A</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B43389)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 208141)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2923:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A] caveat for wives to love their husbands or, Pleasant news from hell. Written in Italian by that grand politician Nicholas Machiavel and now translated into English for a Christmas-gigg.</title>
                  <author>Machiavelli, Niccolò, 1469-1527.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Satire, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:208141:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:208141:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> CAVEAT FOR WIVES To love their HUSBANDS OR, Pleasant News From HELL.</p>
            <p>Written in <hi>Italian</hi> by that Grand Politician NICHOLAS MACHIAVEL And now Translated into <hi>English</hi> for a <hi>CHRISTMAS-GIGG.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:208141:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:208141:3"/>
            <head>A CAVEAT FOR VVIVES To love their HUSBANDS. OR, Pleasant Newes from HELL.</head>
            <byline>Written by <hi>NICHOLAS MACHIAVEL.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Oo God (saies <hi>Machiavel</hi>) in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient memories of the Florentine acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons how that a wholly man, (whose strictnesse of life was in those times had in great admiration) being on a time ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry devoutly at his prayers was wrapt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a vision, wherein he saw the soules of many men who dying in the disgrace of God went to Hell, all or the greatest part of which complained, that their wives
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:208141:4"/>were the occasion of their coming unto that miserable place; whereat <hi>Monos</hi> and <hi>Radamantus</hi> and the rest of the infernall Judges wondred extreamly, nor could they beleive the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies which those men so generally threw upon the femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine sex to have any coherence with trueth, but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints daily encreasing and report of them being made to <hi>Pluto,</hi> it was thought convenient that this case should be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely examined before all the infernall Princes, and that course taken by them which should be thought most conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, either to discover the fallacy, or discerne the trueth. In pursuance of which a council being called, <hi>Pluto</hi> spake to them to this effect. <q>Although I (dearly beloved) by cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestiall disposition and absolute and irrevocable fatality possess this kingdome without controull, none can be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to any judgement heavenly or earthly, yet because it has been always accounted a part of prudence to take others ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicee, have deliberated to be counselled by you how, <hi>I</hi> ought to governe my selfe in a case, which without a prudent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agement, may redound to the infamy of our Kingdome for the soules of all those men who come into this our king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, complaining that their wives have been the cause of their so great misery, and this seeming to us impossible, wee doubt least should wee proceed to give judgement accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this relation, wee might be esteemed too cruel, and not giving it as, sufficiently severe in and too little lovers of justice, and on the one side fall into the scandall of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted light and vaine, on the other side of injust, both which rocks we being willing to shun, we have called you that you might help us with such counsell as might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve this Kingdome, which hitherto hath been maintained without disgrace or infamy, in the same state for the future.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To every one of the Princes respectively, this case seemed to be of great import, and worthy serious consideration, so all of them thought it necessary to find out the trueth, yet they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:208141:4"/>differed extreamly in the manner: some proposed the sending of one, others of more into the world, who under the shape of men might personally informe themselves of the trueth of the complaint, others again thought it might be performed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out so much trouble, by forcing divers soules by several tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to confesse it. But the greater party counselling the sending to earth, that course was determined on. But then another difficulty arose, for there was none who would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly undergoe that travel, it was therefore put to the vote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain who should be sent, &amp; at length to avoid partiality, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the lott should determine it, the lotts being therefore cast, it fell upon <hi>Belfagor</hi> arch-devil (but before his fall from heaven arch angel) who though somwhat unwilling (yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained by <hi>Pluto's</hi> command) fitted himself for the journey, &amp; to be obedient to whatsoever was in the council determined concerning him, which was, That unto whomsoever it should fall to undergoe this business, there should immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be given One Hundred thousand ducats, with which he should depart to this world, and under humane shape take a wife, and with her live ten years, and afterwards feigning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to die, returne to Hell, &amp; by experience relate to his superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours what were the burthens or Commodities of Marriage. It was likewise, declared that during that time he should be subject to all the burthens and ills incident to Mankind, as Poverty, Prisons, discontents, jealousies, sicknesse, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther misfortune unto wich men run, unlesse by his cunning or ingenuity he could free himself from them, <hi>Belfagor</hi> having therefore accepted of these conditions, and the mony comes into the world, and having of his estate provided himself of Horse and Servants enters most honourably into <hi>Florence,</hi> which City above all others in the world, he chose to seate himselfe in, as the most fitting place for those who would live by usury, &amp; causing himself to be called <hi>Roderigoti Castilia</hi> he took a house neere the <hi>Borough</hi> of all <hi>Saints,</hi> and not to let
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:208141:5"/>people know what he was, he gave out, That when young he departed from <hi>Spain</hi> unto <hi>Syria,</hi> and had in <hi>Alleppa</hi> gained his whole estate with which he was now restored into <hi>Italy,</hi> to take a wife in places more humane, and to a civill life, and his disposition more conformable. <hi>Roderigo</hi> was a very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some man, And seemed to be about thirty years of age, which together with the great rules which in few daies he made shew to have, and his civil and courteous carriage made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny noble Citizens of <hi>Florence</hi> who had a great many daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and little money to offer him them in marriage. Among all whom <hi>Roderigo</hi> chose out a most beautifull Damsel called <hi>Honesta,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Amerigo Donati,</hi> who had likewise three sons and three other daughters almost marriagible, and though he was of a most noble family, and of very good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in <hi>Florence,</hi> yet in respect of the great Charge he had, and likewise of his nobilitie, he was indeed but poor. <hi>Roderi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> kept a most magnificent and splendid marriage, nor did he spare of any cost which might make it compleat or equal to any other feasts of the like nature, being by the laws imposed upon him before his coming from hell to be subject to all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane passions; and therefore soon after he began to take pleasure in the honour and pomp of the world, and to love to be praised amongst men, which was some cause of no small expence, but besides that he had not lived long with his wise Madam <hi>Honesta,</hi> but he fell in love with her beyond measure, nor could he live if at any time he saw her sad or displeased; yet so much pride had she with her nobility brought to <hi>Rode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigo</hi>'s house, that <hi>Lucifer</hi> never had so much, and he who had proved that of both, thought this of his wife the greater. But still it increased more and more when she had found out the great love which her husband bore her, whereby she perceivd that she might every way rule over him, so that she doubted not only to command him, but to abuse him with villanous words and scolding language, which though it were an incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:208141:5"/>trouble to <hi>Roderigo,</hi> yet neverthelesse the respect he had to his father in law his friends the tie of matrimony, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all to the love he bore her made him endure it with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. I shall omit the grand expense which he was forced to be at in clothing her after the new modes and fashions which abound in <hi>Florence,</hi> his being forced if he would be at peace with his wife to help to marry her other sisters which cost him no small summe of money, for after this he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained to gain quietnesse from her to send one of her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with cloth into the <hi>Levant,</hi> the other with silkes into the <hi>West,</hi> and to open a shop for the third in <hi>Florence,</hi> by which means he spent the greatest part of his fortunes. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over in the times of <hi>Cornevale</hi> and <hi>Midsommer</hi> when that City of <hi>Florence</hi> by ancient customes use to feast, and the noble Citizens treat one another with sumptuous Banquets, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Honesta</hi> not to be inferiour to other Ladies in those en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments forced <hi>Roderigo</hi> to exceed all others in splendid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. Yet all these charges made not so great a hole in <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derigo</hi>'s estate; as what she spent on her lovers, when under pretence of going for devotion sake to visit some Nunnery she met them at private Conventicles, which though her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band as our women now when they go to Lectures was sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of, yet would he have patiently endured this with the rest; could he but have lived quietly at home, or that by these means he might have had libertie to have peaceably expected his ruine. But it fell out quite contrary, for notwithstanding his insupportable expences, her insolent nature still increased, and there was neither maid-servant not man who could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the house long, whereby <hi>Roderigo</hi>'s affairs went daily to rack by reason he could not keep any servant to look after them; for those Devils who in the habit of servants came with him from hell, chose rather to return into the fire of hell then remain there under herimperious brawlings. <hi>Roderigo</hi> thus enduring this tumultuous and unquiet life had now spent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:208141:6"/>the greatest part of his estate, and began to live upon the hopes of his returns from the <hi>East</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> but having good credit, and still resolving to live according to the port he had first maintained, he in the mean time took up money at inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, which made him begin to be noted as a person in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying condition, to hasten which on a sudden news came, that one of the brothers of Madam <hi>Honesta</hi> had played away all those goods with which he was intrusted, and that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther returning with a ship laden with goods without having ensured them, was with them himself drowned; upon which news the Creditors of <hi>Roderigo</hi> judging him now gone (though they could not yet discover it because their money was not yer due) took counsell together, least he should take occasion to fly before the day of payment. On the other side, <hi>Roderige</hi> seeing his case now desperate, and knowing to what the infernal law bound him, thought by all means to fly, and one morning early mounting on horseback, and living nigh the meddow-gate, gets by it out of the City, but his Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors having watchfull spies upon him, the news of his escape was immediatly brought to the Magistrates, who soon or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the pursuit of him; nor indeed did the Serjeants onely, but the whole City run after him; so that he not being above a mile from the Town when this Rumour was raised, found himself in an ill case, &amp; therefore resolved to leave the road &amp; traverse the fields, but not being able by reason of the many ditches, to go on horseback, alighting, he ran cross the Vineyards till he came to the house of <hi>Iohn Matthews</hi> a Countrey-fellow, to whom he made known his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, promising, that if he would save him from the hands of his enemies who pursued him to make him dye in prison, he would make him rich, and would before his departure give him such an account of the w<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, that if he did not like it he should deliver him into his enemies hands. <hi>John Mathews,</hi> though a country-man, was a stout fellow, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:208141:6"/>knowing he could not lose by the businesse was content to undertake it, and to that effect thrust him under a woodstack, which he had no sooner done but the pursuers arrived, but could neither by threats nor promises perswade <hi>Iohn Mathews</hi> to confesse he saw him, whereupon they passed forward, but not finding him neither that day nor the other, Returned to <hi>Florence.</hi> When all things being quieted <hi>John Mathewes</hi> takes <hi>Roderigo</hi> from under the stack, and requires him to perform his promise, to which <hi>Roderigo</hi> answered, Brother, thou hast obliged me very much, and I am resolved by all meanes to satisfie thee, and because thou shalt believ that I can do it, Ile tell thee who I am. Here hee recounted who he was the laws he had to come out of hell, and the taking of his wife &amp;c. And then told him that the way whereby he would make him Rich should in fumm bee this, That when he should hear that any woman was possest with an evil spirit, he should beleive that it was he that was within her, and assured him that he would never go out till he came to fetch him, whereby he might have occasion to make himself be paid as he pleased, and having made this conclusion he vanished. Nor were there many daies past, but there was spread abroad a Rumor throughout all <hi>Florence</hi> how a daughter of Mr. <hi>Ambrogio A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>madei</hi> was possest with a Devil, nor were her parents wanting to use all those remedies which are commonly used in <hi>Italy</hi> in like cases, puting on her head the Cap of St. <hi>Zanoby</hi> and the mantle of St. <hi>Geo. Gualberto,</hi> all which things <hi>Rode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigo</hi> laught at, but to make it clearly appear that it was a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, he disputed in latine and discovered the sins of many, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which he told of a Frier, who under a young Friers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, had kept a wench four years in his Cell, In the mean time no remedy was found, till <hi>Iohn Mathewes</hi> hearing of it, proffered Mr. <hi>Ambrogio</hi> to cure his daughter for five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Florines which he willingly agreeing to give, <hi>Iohn Mathews</hi> causing several masses to be said to colour the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, whispered to <hi>Roderigo</hi> that he was come, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:208141:7"/>he should be as good as his word, to which <hi>Roderigo</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered that he was content, but that he was not yet enough to make him rich, and that therefore as he was gone out of her, he would enter into the King of <hi>Naples</hi> daughter where he might have what reward he pleased, and that then he should trouble him no more. Which words ended he went out of the maid, to the pleasure and admiration of all <hi>Florence,</hi> nor past their much time but the news was spread that the King of <hi>Naples</hi> daughter was possessed, and no remedy being found, <hi>Iohn Mathewes,</hi> whose fame was now abroad, was sent for, who being arrived, after some feigned ceremony cured her, but <hi>Roderigo</hi> before he parted out, told him, Thou seest (saith hee) that I have observed my promise in making thee rich, and therfore being disobliged in that, I am not bound to thee in any thing whatsoever, therefore be content to come no more before me, for if thou doest, as I have hitherto don thee good, so I will for the future do thee harm. Thus <hi>Iohn Mathews</hi> haveing finished his work at <hi>Naples,</hi> returned to <hi>Florence</hi> very rich (for the King of <hi>Naples</hi> had given fifty thousand ducats) thinking now to enjoy himself, and not dreaming that <hi>Roderi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> meant to offend him, but those thoughts of his were soon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbed by certain new's from <hi>Prance,</hi> that the Kings daughter there was possessed which extreamly perplexed <hi>Iohn Matthews</hi> both to thinke of the power of that King, and of the words which <hi>Roderigo</hi> had spoke him, but whilest he was thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed (no other remedy being found) comes a messenger to desire him to come and cast the Devil our, to whom he feined himself sick and unable to go, whereupon the King sent Ambassadors to the senate who forced him much against his will, being therefore come to <hi>Paris,</hi> he first began to argue with the King, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>ll him, That it was true that he had here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore cured some who had been possessed with Devils, but it could not from thence be thought that he was to cure all, for that there were some Devils of so perverse a nature that they feared neither threats nor inchantments, nor any Religion, but
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:208141:7"/>however he would doe his duty, and if he could not prevail, desired excuse and Pardon, to which the King passionately answered, that if he did not doe it he would hang him, <hi>Iohn Mathewes</hi> was extreamly troubled at this, but however, putting on a a good heart, he caused the Kings daughter to be brought before him, and whispering in her ear, humbly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends himself to <hi>Roderigo,</hi> remembring him of the benefit he had done him and telling of how much Ingratitude he would be example of, if he should abandon him in so great ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity. To which <hi>Roderigo</hi> answered, ah Villain, Traytor, how durst thou appear again before me, dost thinke to boast that thou art made Rich by my means, I'le make thee and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one else know how to give and take away at pleasure, and therfore before thou goest from hence Ile have thee hanged, Wherupon <hi>Iohn Mathews,</hi> not seeing other remedy at present, thought to try his fortune another way, and sending away the possessed, tels the King, that as he had said before there were some perverse divels whom nothing could prevaile with, and this was one of them, but however he would try a farther experience, which if it prevailed his Majestie had what he desired, if not, he should be at his mercy, which he hoped he would use with that compasion which his innocence deserved. In the mean time (sai's he) your Majestie shall erect a large theatre, capable to containe all your Barons, and the Clergy of this City, the theater shall be covered with cloth of Gold and silk, and in the midst of it an altar erected and on the Sunday morning your Majestie, with the Clergy, and all the Princes and Barons of your Realm, with Kingly Pomp and splendid and rich habiliments shall assemble upon it, haveing first celebrated a Solemn masse, shall cause your daughter to be brought, and moreover in one corner of the theatre shall be placed at least twenty persons with Trumpets, Hornes, Drums, Cornets, Symbals, and all manner of loud Musick which when I lift up my hat, shall, sounding those in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments,
<pb facs="tcp:208141:8"/>advance towards the Altar, which things together with some other secret Remedies will, I hope, dispossess the Devil, These things were punctually ordered according to his desire, and Sunday Morning being come, and the theatre fild with noble personages and the whole place with people, the masse being celebrated, the possessed was brought to the Altar, conducted by two Bishops, accompanied with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther persons of quality. But when <hi>Roderigo</hi> saw all this pomp and splendor, he began to reason with himself thus, what hath this foolish fellow thought to doe, doth he think to fright me with all this show: do's he not know that I am used to see the pomp of Heaven, and the Furies of hell? but I shall chastise him. In the mean time <hi>Iohn Mathewes</hi> coming towards him, began again to pray him that he should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; oh (sai's he) you have found out a fine invention, what dost think to do with all this foppery, dost think by this to escape my power, or the Kings anger? no, Ile have thee surely hang'd, and thus one praying, and the other still deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Iohn Matthews</hi> thought fit not to loose any more time, lifting up his hat, the loud Musick advanced sounding, at which sudden noise <hi>Roderigo</hi> amazed, demanded what the meaning of it was, to which <hi>Iohn Matthews</hi> replied, my <hi>Roderigo,</hi> tis thy wife who is coming to find thee out here. Twas beyond belief to think how much <hi>Roderigo</hi> was moved to hear his wife named, but so much it was, that not standing to think whether it was possible or not that she should be there, without replying any thing, in a great fright he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately fled away, leaving the Kings daughter dispossessed, and chose rather to return to Hell, there to give an account of his actions, then again with so many disasters and discontents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe the matrimonial yoak. And thus <hi>Belfagor</hi> returned to Hell to give account how much mischief a wife breeds in a house, and <hi>Iohn Matthews</hi> who knew more then the Devil went merrily home.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:208141:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>